Welcome back and in the last lesson we explicitly told TypeScript what types of variable
should have.
But what have I told you that TypeScript is smart enough to yes or figure out on its own
what the type is.
That's called type inference and it's one of the reasons TypeScript fills so natural
to use.
So what exactly is Type inference?
That's when TypeScript can automatically determine the type of a variable based on its initial
value.
So we don't always need to annotate types manually.
TypeScript does the happy lifting for us.
Let's have a look at a few examples of this, so let's just remove what we have here.
So we can do let my bar equals Alice.
So if we hover over it we can see that isn't third that this is a string because the quote
marks around it.
Let's do a few more, let's age equal 30.
If we hover over this we can see that isn't third that this is a number and you can do
let's is admin equals true and if we hover over this we can see that it's inferred
that this is of type boolean.
When you sign a value to a variable, TypeScript analyzes the value and locks in the type.
Now if you try and assign the type later it's going to throw an error.
So for example if we come in here and we say for example my bar equals 30 then it's going
to give us straight away a little red squiggly line that we can't now change the type
because it's been assigned as a string at the beginning and now we're trying to change
it to an integer and the same is the case of something like age.
If we set that to maybe 30 we can get an error that we're trying to assign a string to
it but if we try and set it to say 35 then that's absolutely fine because we're still
modifying the existing variable and it's now set as a number.
Now let's do a quick little game here which is called guess the type it's not the world's
most exciting so let country equals uk now rather than hovering over it can you guess
what these types are if I do temperature equals 21.5 let's do a lit is logged in equals
false and some more types that we haven't yet talked about let's use a name is Bob with
age of 25 and the last one let's colors equals red, green and maybe blue.
Try and guess what these types will be inferred as and then you can see the actual results
by hovering over it with the cursor or so let's do country that's a string this is a number
even a fact it's actually a kind of floating number we then have a Boolean we then have
an object or a type of user in this structure and we also have an array of strings so hopefully
you managed to guess is all correctly so if types scripts can infer types why should
we bother than writing them out now we should use inference when the value is pretty obvious
so for example the one here is pretty obvious to us that is a string and this one specifically
not also is obvious this is a Boolean or you're prototyping quickly so you know you're
just doing something in a hurry you're just wanting to quickly throw something out as an
experiment then perhaps you can't be bothered to explicitly set the types or you're working
with a very simple data like in this case here and these ones is fairly obvious to anybody
reading the code and to TypeScript what you're trying to do but you should use explicit
types and that's when we actually specifically set it so for example Boolean this is an
explicit type whereas these are implicit types so explicit type should be used when we want
to clarify our intent so in that case where we have like let my var equals 1 now it's not entirely
clear are we going to be using this as an integer at some point or are we wanting it strictly
as a string so this is where we want to specifically say this is going to be a string because you
know this could be yeah we want to try and add one to it at some point and that's not going to
work it also you should use explicit types when you're designing public APIs or libraries or you're
using complex or generic structures so think of inference as your default and explicit types as
your precision tool that's the way I like to think of these things now one thing to be aware of
is that TypeScript can infer return types or functions but not parameter types we need to
annotate those manually so let's do a quick example of a function so function and of course if
we've been writing JavaScript to be well aware what this could look like and say name and so we're
going to define the structure like this or the function like this and notice we need to actually
specify a want to specify a type for this so we need to say string and then we can do return
hello and then something like hello well to all let's just do back ticks here and do hello
dollar name is a better example right so name must be typed explicitly is the return type
is actually inferred and you can see as we hover over it that the name is a string and the return
type is what specified in the colon afterwards or the function which is also a string
let's do a couple more different examples and let's do let product equals curly brace ID one title
say book and price 999 to let's see what TypeScript infers this type has and it
infers is a effectly a type of object structure let's try and change the title so product
title let's set to maybe 23 and you can see now it's actually an unknown that the title property
in this object is of type string again we try and change for example the price and let's set the price
to 23 and it's also going to throw an error so you can see how TypeScript is protecting us from doing
rubber city things let's do another example and do let discount equals null
and let's now try and see what type TypeScript thinks as things is of type any so at this stage
is not really sure what it could be so if we do discount equals 23 and it's going to allow
that to come through because it knows that this we have actually specified what this type should be
if we come in later and do discount equals 23 it's also going to allow that because
we haven't actually specified the type again so this is where we want to explicitly set something
because what is discount is a number or what is it so if we now set that to a number
it's going to throw an error over here because we are trying to assign it to the string
let's also going to complain because we are setting that as type null
okay so you can see type inference makes TypeScript feel intuitive and flexible
it allows us to write clean code without sacrificing safety so in the next lesson we're going to
explore arrays and tuples and how to type them how to use them and how to avoid column mistakes